Let's begin with a story.
دعونا نبدأ بقصة.
Once upon a time --
ذات يوم --
well actually less than two years ago --
حسناً في الحقيقة قبل اقل من عامين --
in a kingdom not so very far away,
في مملكة ليست بالبعيدة،
there was a man
كان هناك رجل
who traveled many miles
يسافر اميالاً عديدة
to come to work at the jewel in the kingdom's crown --
ليحضر ليعمل في جوهرة في تاج المملكة --
an internationally famous company.
شركة دولية شهيرة
Let's call it Island Networks.
لندعها شبكات الجزيرة
Now this kingdom had many resources
الآن هذه المملكة لديها الكثير من الموارد
and mighty ambitions,
وطموحات جبارة،
but the one thing it lacked was people.
ولكن الشيئ الذي ينقصها هو الناس.
And so it invited workers from around the world
وبالتالي فقد دعت العاملين من حول العالم
to come and help it build the nation.
للحضور والمساعدة في بناء الأمة.
But in order to enter and to stay
ولكن لكي تدخل وتقيم
these migrants had to pass a few tests.
فإنه يجب على المهاجرين اجتياز بعض الاختبارات.
And so it was, our man presented himself
وقد كان ، قدم رجلنا نفسه
to authorities in the kingdom,
للسلطات في المملكة،
looking forward to settling into his new life.
وتطلع الى الاستقرار في حياته الجديدة.
But then something unexpected happened.
ولكن حدث مالم يكن في الحسبان.
The medical personnel who took blood samples from the man
الشخصية الطبية التي اخذت عينات من الرجل
never actually told him what they were testing for.
لم تخبره بالفعل عن الفحوصات التي يجرونها.
He wasn't offered counseling before or after the test,
لم يجرى عليه اية كشوفات طبية قبل او بعد الفحص،
which is best medical practice.
حيث ان هذه هي افضل الممارسات الطبية.
He was never informed of the results of the test.
لم يتم ابلاغه بنتائج الفحص.
And yet, a couple of weeks later,
وبعد مرور اسبوعين،
he was picked up and taken to prison
تم القبض عليه واودع السجن
where he was subjected to a medical exam,
حيث كان موضع فحص طبي،
including a full-body search
يتضمن فحص شامل لجسمه
in full view of the others in the cell.
والجميع يشاهد في الزنزانة.
He was released, but then a day or two later,
تم الافراج عنه ، ولكن بعد مرور يوم او يومين،
he was taken to the airport and he was deported.
تم اخذه الى المطار وتم ترحيله.
What on earth did this man do
ماذا بربكم فعل هذا الرجل
to merit this treatment?
ليتلقى هذه المعاملة ؟
What was his terrible crime?
ماذا كانت جريمته الشنعاء ؟
He was infected with HIV.
كان مصابا بعدوى فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
Now the kingdom is one of about 50 countries
الآن اصبحت هذه المملكة واحدة من نحو 50 دولة
that imposes restrictions on the entry or stay
تضع قيوداً على الدخول والبقاء
of people living with HIV.
على الاشخاص الذين لديهم فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
The kingdom argues
احتجت المملكة
that its laws allow it to detain or deport foreigners
ان قوانينها تسمح لها بترحيل او اعتقال الاجانب
who pose a risk to the economy
الذين يشكلون خطراً على الاقتصاد
or the security or the public health
او الامن او الصحة العامة
or the morals of the state.
او الروح المعنوية للدولة.
But these laws, when applied to people living with HIV,
ولكن هذه القوانين ، عند تطبيقها على الاشخاص الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
are a violation of international human rights agreements
هي خرق للاتفاقيات الدولية لحقوق الانسان
to which these countries are signatories.
والتي كان هذه الدول من الموقعين عليها.
But you know what?
ولكن هل تعلمون؟
Matters of principle aside,
بتنحية المبدأ جانباً،
practically speaking, these laws drive HIV underground.
ومن وجهة نظر عملية ، فإن هذه القوانين تدفع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية تحت الارض.
People are less likely to come forth
الناس في العادة لا يحبذون ان يأتوا
to be tested or treated or to disclose their condition,
لكي يتم فحصهم او الافصاح عن حالتهم،
none of which helps these individuals
لا أحد يساعد هؤلاء الافراد
or the communities these laws purport to protect.
او الجماعات، ان هذه القوانين تضمن الحماية.
Today we can prevent the transmission of HIV.
اليوم نحن نمنع انتقال فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
And with treatment, it is a manageable condition.
وبالعلاج ، فهو حالة يمكن السيطرة عليها.
We are very far from the days
نحن بعيدين جداً عن هذه الايام
when the only practical response to dread disease
عندما كانت الاستجابة العملية الوحيدة للمرض المفزع
was to have banished the afflicted --
هي نفي المصاب بالعدوى --
like this, "The Exile of the Leper."
مثل هذا , "منفى مرضى البرص."
So you tell me why, in our age of science,
اذن اخبروني لماذا ، في عصر العلم الذي نعيش فيه
we still have laws and policies
مازالت لدينا قوانين وسياسات
which come from an age of superstition.
تأتي من عصر الخرافات.
Time for a quick show of hands.
حان الوقت لعرض سريع للايدي.
Who here has been touched by HIV --
من هنا كان قريباً من فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية --
either because you yourself have the virus
اما لأنك بنفسك لديك هذا الفيروس
or you have a family member or a friend or a colleague
او ان لديك احد افراد عائلتك او صديق او زميل
who is living with HIV?
تعايش مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية؟
Hands up.
ارفعوا الايدي.
Wow. Wow.
واو. واو.
That's a significant number of us.
هذا يعني عددا كبيراً منا.
You know better than anyone
انت تعلمون اكثر من اي شخص آخر
that HIV brings out
أن فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية ابرز لدينا
the best and the worst in humanity.
أفضل وأسوأ ما في الانسانية.
And the laws reflect these attitudes.
والقوانين التي تعكس هذه المواقف.
I'm not just talking about laws on the books,
أنا لا أتحدث فقط عن القوانين التي في الكتب،
but laws as they are enforced on the streets
ولكن القوانين التي يفرضونها في الشوارع
and laws as they are decided in the courts.
والقوانين التي يسنونها في المحاكم.
And I'm not just talking about laws
وأنا لا أتحدث فقط عن القوانين
as they relate to people living with HIV,
التي تتعلق بالاشخاص الناس الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية،
but people who are at greatest risk of infection --
ولكن الناس الذين يتعرضون لاعظم مخاطر العدوى --
people such as those who inject drugs or sex workers
الناس الذين يقومون بحقن المخدرات او الذين يمارسون الجنس
or men who have sex with men
او الرجال الذين يمارسون الجنس مع رجال
or transgendered persons
او الاشخاص المتحولين جنسياً
or migrants or prisoners.
او المهاجرين او المسجونين.
And in many parts of the world that includes women and children
وفي كثير من أجزاء في العالم التي تشتمل على نساء واطفال
who are especially vulnerable.
الذين هم ضعفاء بالخصوص.
Now there are laws in many parts of the world
الآن هناك قوانين في كثير من اجزاء العالم
which reflect the best of human nature.
تعكس افضل طبائع الانسان.
These laws treat people touched by HIV
هذه القوانين تتعامل مع الاشخاص المصابين بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
with compassion and acceptance.
بالشفقة والقبول
These laws respect universal human rights
هذه القوانين تحترم حقوق الانسان العالمية
and they are grounded in evidence.
وهي ترتكز على الدليل.
These laws ensure that people living with HIV
تضمن هذه القوانين ان الاشخاص الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
and those at greatest risk
و هؤلاء الاشخاص الذين يتعرضون لأعظم المخاطر
are protected from violence and discrimination
هم محميين من العنف والتمييز
and that they get access to prevention and to treatment.
وأنهم يستطيعون الدخول الى الوقاية والعلاج.
Unfortunately, these good laws
للأسف ، هذه القوانين الجميلة
are counter-balanced by a mass
تتوازن مع
of really bad law --
القوانين السيئة بالفعل --
law which is grounded in moral judgement
القانون الذي يرتكز على الحكم المعنوي
and in fear and in misinformation,
و في خوف و في عدم توفر معلومات
laws which specifically punish people living with HIV
قوانين تعاقب الاشخاص الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية خاصة
or those at greatest risk.
او اولئك المعرضون لمخاطر عظيمة.
These laws fly in the face of science,
تطير هذه القوانين في وجه العلم
and they are grounded in prejudice
وهي ترتكز على الاجحاف
and in ignorance and in a rewriting of tradition
و في جهل و في اعادة كتابة العادات
and a selective reading of religion.
والقراءة المنتقاة من الدين.
But you know what? You don't have to take my word for it.
ولكن هل تعلمون ؟ ليس عليكم اخذ كلمتي مجردة
We're going to hear from two people
سنستمع من شخصين
who are on the sharp end of the law.
يتبوءان مركزاً دقيقاً من القانون
The first is Nick Rhoades. He's an American.
الأول هو نيك روهاديس هو امريكي
And he was convicted under the U.S. State of Iowa's law
وقد تم ادانته تحت قانون ولاية ايوا الامريكية
on HIV transmission and exposure --
بنقل فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية وتعريض الناس للخطر
neither of which offense he actually committed.
وهو لم يقترف أياً من هاتين الجريمتين
(Video) Nick Rhoades: If something is against the law
(فيديو) نيك روهاديس: لو كان هناك شيئاً ضد القانون
then that is telling society
إن هذا يخبر المجتمع
that is unacceptable, that's bad behavior.
ان هذا غير مقبول ، هذا سلوك سيئ
And I think the severity of that punishment
وأعتقد أن خطورة هذه العقوبة
tells you how bad you are as a person.
تخبرك مدى سوءك كشخص
You're a class B felon,
انت مجرم من درجة تانية
lifetime sex offender.
معتدٍ جنسي لمدى الحياة
You are a very, very, very bad person.
انت شخص سيئ جدا جدا جدا
And you did a very, very, very bad thing.
وقد اقترفت شيئاً سيئاً جدا جدا جدا
And so that's just programmed into you.
وان هذا قد تم ببرجمته في داخلك
And you go through the correctional system
وانت تمضي في نظام اصلاحي
and everyone's telling you the same thing.
والكل يخبرك بنفس الشيء
And you're just like, I'm a very bad person.
وانت فقط مثل ، انا شخص سيئ جداً
Shereen El-Feki: It's not just a question
شيرين الفقي : هذا ليس سؤال فقط
of unfair or ineffective laws.
عن قوانين ظالمة وغير فعالة
Some countries have good laws,
بعض البلاد لديها قوانين جيدة
laws which could stem the tide of HIV.
قوانين من شأنها ايقاف انتشار فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
The problem is that these laws are flouted.
المشكلة ان هذه القوانين قد تم الاستهزاء بها
Because stigma gives unofficial license
لأن وصمة العار تعطي رخصة غير رسمية
to treat people living with HIV
لمعاملة الاشخاص الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
or those at greatest risk
او اولئك الذين يتعرضون لاعظم المخاطر
unlike other citizens.
بكل غير مشابه للمواطنين العاديين
And this is exactly what happened
وهذا بالضبط ما حدث
to Helma and Dongo from Namibia.
لهيلما و دونجو من ناميبيا
(Video) Hilma: I found out
(فيديو) هيلما: لقد اكتشفت
when I went to the hospital for a pregnancy check-up.
عند ذهابي للمستشفى لفحص الحمل
The nurse announced that every pregnant woman
فان الممرضة اعلنت ان كل امرأة حامل
must also be tested for HIV that day.
عليها ان تقوم بفحص فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية في هذا اليوم
I took the test and the result showed I was positive.
وقمت بالفحص وأظهرت النتائج بانني حاملة للمرض
That's the day I found out.
اكتشفت هذا في ذلك اليوم.
The nurse said to me, "Why should you people bcome pregnant
قالت لي الممرضة "لماذا يجب عليكم ايها الناس ان تحملوا
when you know you are HIV positive?
عندما تعلمون انكم مصابون بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية؟
Why are you pregnant when you are living positive?"
لماذا تكونين حاملاً وانت تعيشين مع المرض؟
I am sure now that is the reason they sterilized me.
انا متاكدة الآن أن هذا هو السبب وراء تعقيمي.
Because I am HIV positive.
لأنني احمل فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
They didn't give the forms to me
لم يعطوني النماذج
or explain what was in the form.
او شرح ماذا كان في النموذج
The nurse just came with it
لقد اتت الممرضة بها فقط
already marked where I had to sign.
بعلامة توضح مكان التوقيع.
And with the labor pain,
ومع الآم الولادة،
I didn't have the strength to ask them to read it to me.
لم يكن لدي القوة لأطلب منهم قراءته علي
I just signed.
لقد وقعت فقط.
SE: Hilma and Nick and our man in the kingdom
شيرين: هيلما و نيك ورجلنا في المملكة
are among the 34 million people living with HIV
من بين 34 مليون شخص يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
according to recent estimates.
طبقاً لآخر احصائيات.
They're the lucky ones
هم من المحظوظين
because they're still alive.
لأنهم مازالوا احياء.
According to those same estimates,
وطبقاً لمثل هذه الاحصائيات،
in 2010 1.8 million people died
في عام 2010 مات 1.8 مليون شخص
of AIDS related causes.
لأسباب تتعلق بالايدز.
These are terrible and tragic figures.
هذه ارقام مخيفة ومأساوية.
But if we look a little more broadly into the statistics,
ولكن اذا نظرنا بشمولية قليلاً الى الاحصائيات
we actually see some reason for hope.
فاننا نرى حقاً بعض الاسباب للأمل
Looking globally, the number of new infections of HIV is declining.
نظرة حول العالم ، فان عدد المصابين بالعدوى حديثاً بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية في تناقص
And looking globally as well,
وبالنظر حول العالم ايضاً
deaths are also starting to fall.
فان الموت كذلك بدأ في النقصان
There are many reasons for these positive developments,
هناك بعض الاسباب لهذه التطورات الايجابية
but one of the most remarkable
ولكن احد اكثرها وضوحاً
is in the increase in the number of people around the world
هو زيادة عدد الناس حول العالم
on anti-retroviral therapy,
المستخدمين للادوية المضادة للفيروس
the medicines they need to keep their HIV in check.
التي يحتاجونها للحفاظ على فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية تحت السيطرة.
Now there are still many problems.
الان لازال هناك بعض المشكلات.
Only about half of the people who need treatment
فقط حوالي نصف الناس الذين يحتاجون للعلاج
are currently receiving it.
هم بالفعل يتلقونه الان.
In some parts of the world --
في بعض اجزاء من العالم --
like here in the Middle East and North Africa --
مثل هنا في الشرق الاوسط وشمال افريقيا
new infections are rising and so are deaths.
الاصابات الجديدة في زيادة وكذلك الموتى.
And the money, the money we need
والمال، المال الذي نحتاجه
for the global response to HIV,
لتحرك عالمي لفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
that is shrinking.
يتضاءل.
But for the first time
ولكن للمرة الاولى
in three decades into this epidemic
خلال ثلاثة عقود من هذا الوباء
we have a real chance to come to grips with HIV.
لدينا فرصة حقيقية للسيطرة على فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
But in order to do that
ولكن لعمل ذلك
we need to tackle an epidemic of really bad law.
نحن نحتاج لمعالجة قانون خاص بالوباء سيئ بالفعل.
It's for this reason
ولهذا السبب
that the Global Commission on HIV and the Law,
فان اللجنة العالمية لفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية والقانون
of which I'm a member,
والتي اكون احد اعضائها
was established by the agencies of the United Nations --
تم تأسيسها بواسطة الوكالات التي تتبع الامم المتحدة --
to look at the ways that legal environments
للنظر في الوسائل التي تنتهجها البيئات القانونية
are affecting people living with HIV
التي تؤثر على الناس الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
and those at greatest risk,
واولئك الذين يتعرضون لاعظم المخاطر،
and to recommend what should be done
والتوصية بما يمكن عمله
to make the law an ally, not an enemy,
لجعل القانون حليفاً ليس عدواً،
of the global response to HIV.
للاستجابة العالمية لفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
Let me give you just one example
دعوني اعطيكم مثالاً واحداً
of the way a legal environment
عن الطريقة التي يمكن للبيئة القانونية
can make a positive difference.
ان تصنع فرقاً ايجابياً.
People who inject drugs
الاشخاص الذين يحقنون المخدرات
are one of those groups I mentioned.
هم احد اولئك المجموعات التي ذكرتها.
They're at high risk of HIV
فهم على خطر كبير بالنسبة للاصابة بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
through contaminated injection equipment
من خلال معدات الحقن الملوثة
and other risk-related behaviors.
و السلوكيات المتعلقة بالمخاطر الاخرى
In fact, one in every 10 new infections of HIV
في الواقع ،هناك شخص من بين كل 10 مصابين جدد بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
is among people who inject drugs.
هم ممن يتعاطون المخدرات عن طريق الحقن
Now drug use or possession
الان استخدام المخدرات او حيازتها
is illegal in almost every country.
غير قانوني تقريباً في كل البلاد.
But some countries take a harder line on this than others.
ولكن هناك دولاً تتخذ اجراءات اشد صرامة من الاخرى.
In Thailand people who use drugs,
في تايلاند الناس الذين يتعاطون المخدرات
or are merely suspected of using drugs,
او بالكاد يشتبه في انهم يتعاطونها،
are placed in detention centers,
يوضعون في مراكز اعتقال،
like the one you see here,
مثل الذي ترونه هنا،
where they are supposed to clean up.
حيث من المفترض ان يتم تنظيفهم.
There is absolutely no evidence
ليس هناك دليلاً على الاطلاق
to show that throwing people into detention
ان قذف الناس في معتقل
cures their drug dependence.
يشفيهم من اعتمادهم على المخدرات.
There is, however, ample evidence
هناك ، على اي حال ، دليل وافر
to show that incarcerating people
يظهر ان حبس الناس
increases their risk of HIV and other infections.
يزيد من خطر اصابتهم بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية او اي عدوى اخرى.
We know how to reduce HIV transmission and other risks
نحن نعلم كيف نقلل من انتقال فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية والمخاطر الاخرى
in people who inject drugs.
في الناس الذين يحقنون بالمخدرات.
It's called harm reduction,
يطلق عليه تقليل الضرر
and it involves, among other things,
وهو يتضمن ، بين اشياء اخرى
providing clean needles and syringes,
تزويدهم بابر وحقن نظيفة
offering opioid substitution therapy
اعطاء بدائل علاجية للافيون
and other evidence-based treatments
وعلاجات اخرى مبنية على أدلة
to reduce drug dependence.
لتقليل الاعتماد على المخدرات
It involves providing information
تتضمن توفير المعلومات
and education and condoms
والتثقيف والواقيات
to reduce HIV transmission,
لتقليل انتقال فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
and also providing HIV testing
وكذلك توفير فحص الاصابة بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
and counseling and treatment
والاستشارة والعلاج
should people become infected.
عندما يصاب الناس.
Where the legal environment allows for harm reduction
حيث تسمح البيئة القانونية بتقليل الضرر
the results are striking.
النتائج مدهشة
Australia and Switzerland
استراليا وسويسرا
were two countries which introduced harm reduction
دولتان قامتا بتطبيق تقليل الضرر
very early on in their HIV epidemics,
في وقت مبكر في مقاومتهم لوباء فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
and they have a very low rate of HIV
ولديهم معدل منخفض جداُ من الاصابة بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
among injecting drug users.
بين مستخدمي المخدرات عن طريق الحقن
The U.S. and Malaysia
الولايات المتحدة الامريكية وماليزيا
came to harm reduction a little later,
اتوا الى تقليل الضرر متأخرين قليلاً
and they have higher rates of HIV in these populations.
ولديهم معدلات أعلى بالاصابة بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية بالنسبة لعدد سكانهم
Thailand and Russia, however,
ولكن تايلاند وروسيا ,
have resisted harm reduction
قاوموا تقليل الضرر
and have stringent laws
ولديهم قوانين اكثر صرامة
which punish drug use.
تعاقب استخدام المخدرات.
And hey, surprise,
و هنا المفاجأة
very high rates of HIV among people who are injecting drugs.
معدلات عالية جداً بالاصابة فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية بين الناس الذين يتعاطون المخدرات عن طريق الحقن
At the Global Commission we have studied the evidence,
في اللجنة العالمية قمنا بدراسة الدليل
and we've heard the experiences
واستمعنا للخبراء
of over 700 people from 140 countries.
مايفوق 700 شخص من 140 دولة
And the trend? Well the trend is clear.
والاتجاه ؟ حسناً كان الاتجاه واضحاً
Where you criminalize people living with HIV
حيث تجرم الناس الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
or those at greatest risk,
او اولئك الذين يتعرضون لاعظم المخاطر
you fuel the epidemic.
فأنت تغذي الوباء
Now coming up with a vaccine for HIV
الان اكتشفوا لقاحاً لفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
or a cure for AIDS --
او شفاء من الايدز
now that's rocket science.
الان هذا انتصار للعلم.
But changing the law isn't.
ولكن تغيير القانون ، ليس كذلك
And in fact, a number of countries are starting to make progress
وفي الواقع، فان عددا من الدول بدأت باحراز تقدم
on a number of points.
في عدد من النقاط
To begin, countries need to review their legislation
في البداية ، على الدول مراجعة قوانينها
as it touches HIV and vulnerable groups.
حيث انها تؤثر في المصابين بفيروس نقص المناعة البشرية والفئات الضعيفة
On the back of those reviews,
وعلى ظهر هذه المراجعات
governments should repeal laws
فعلى الحكومات إلغاء القوانين
that punish or discriminate against people living with HIV
التي تقضي بالمعاقبة او التمييز ضد الاشخاص الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
or those at greatest risk.
أو اولئك الذين يتعرضون لاعظم المخاطر
Repealing a law isn't easy,
حذف القوانين ليس بالأمر السهل
and it's particularly difficult
وهو عملياً صعب
when it relates to touchy subjects like drugs and sex.
عندما يتعلق الامر بموضوعات حساسة مثل المخدرات والجنس
But there's plenty you can do while that process is underway.
ولكن هناك الكثير يمكنكم عمله بينما هذه العملية تحت التنفيذ
One of the key points is to reform the police
احدى النقاط الهامة هي اعادة هيكلة الشرطة
so that they have better practices on the ground.
وبالتالي سيكون لديهم ممارسات افضل على الارض
So for example, outreach workers
فعلى سبيل المثال ، توعية العاملين
who are distributing condoms to vulnerable populations
الذين يوزعون الواقيات للكثافات السكانية المعرضة للمرض
are not themselves subject to police harassment
بانهم ليسوا عرضة للتحرش البوليسي
or abuse or arbitrary arrest.
أو المضايقة أو الاعتقال
We can also train judges
كما يمكننا كذلك تدريب القضاة
so that they find flexibilities in the law
بحيث يجدون مرونة في القانون
and so that they rule on the side of tolerance
ومن ثم يديرون الامر من جهة التسامح
rather than prejudice.
وليس من جهة التحامل
We can retool prisons
نستطيع ان نعيد تجهيز السجون
so that HIV prevention and harm reduction
بما يحقق التقليل من الضرر والوقاية من فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
is available to prisoners.
للسجناء
The key to all this is reinforcing civil society.
والمفتاح لكل ذلك هو اعادة تسليح المجتمع المدني
Because civil society is key
لأن المجتمع المدني هو الحل
to raising awareness among vulnerable groups
لزيادة الوعي بين المجموعات المهمشة
of their legal rights.
عن حقوقهم القانونية
But awareness needs action.
ولكن الوعي يحتاج لفعل
And so we need to ensure
وبالتالي فاننا نحتاج لضمان
that these people who are living with HIV
ان هؤلاء الناس الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
or at greatest risk of HIV
او اولئك الذين يتعرضون لأعظم المخاطر
have access to legal services
لديهم القدرة للدخول الى الخدمات القانونية
and they have equal access to the courts.
ولديهم قدر متساوي من الدخول الى المحاكم
And also important is talking to communities
وكذلك من المهم التحدث الى المجتمعات
so that we change interpretations
وبالتالي نغير تفسير
of religious or customary law,
الدين و القوانين الوضعية
which is too often used
والتي تستخدم بكثرة
to justify punishment and fuel stigma.
لتبرير العقاب و تغذية الوباء
For many of us here
لمعظمنا هنا
HIV is not an abstract threat.
فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية ليس مجرد تهديد
It hits very close to home.
انه يضرب قريباً من كل دار
The law, on the other hand,
القانون ، على الجانب الآخر
can seem remote, arcane, the stuff of specialists,
يبدو بعيداً ، غامضاً ، مليء بالمتخصصين
but it isn't.
ولكنه ليس كذلك
Because for those of us who live in democracies,
لأن هؤلاء مننا الذين يعيشون في الديمقراطيات
or in aspiring democracies,
او في الديمقراطيات الملهمة
the law begins with us.
القانون يبدأ بنا
Laws that treat people living with HIV
القوانين تتعامل مع الاشخاص الذين يعيشون مع فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
or those at greatest risk with respect
او اولئك المعرضون لمخاطر كبيرة باحترام
start with the way that we treat them ourselves: as equals.
بدءاً من الطريقة التي نعامل بها انفسنا على قدم المساواة
If we are going to stop the spread of HIV in our lifetime,
لو اننا سنوقف زحف فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية في حياتنا
then that is the change we need to spread.
اذن ، هذا هو التغيير الذي نريد ان ننشره
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)